<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>不辍弦歌</title>
    <link>http://example.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on 不辍弦歌</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://example.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Customizing pdf output of Pandoc</title>
      <link>http://example.org/posts/2019-10-customizing-pdf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/posts/2019-10-customizing-pdf/</guid>
      <description>I am writing my PhD thesis and instead of using LaTeX, I want to write it in markdown together with Pandoc. This has several merits. I can easily transform the markdown file to docx for my supervisor to revise. It can also easily be transformed to pdf files through LaTeX. However, the default pdf output doesn&amp;rsquo;t conform to the format my school requires. What I am going to do is to customize the pdf format to meet the standard of my school.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scraping all the texts of Luxun(鲁迅) from the Internet using Python (用Python爬取《鲁迅全集》)</title>
      <link>http://example.org/posts/2019-10-12-scraping-luxun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/posts/2019-10-12-scraping-luxun/</guid>
      <description>I want to do some text mining practices on the texts of Luxun(鲁迅), a great Chinese writer. The first step is to get all the texts by Luxun, and I have no time typing all the texts word by word. So I decided to srape the texts from an online source.
Source of the texts The texts of Luxun are scraped from 子夜星网. As it claimed, it contains all the texts in the Complete works of Luxun(鲁迅全集).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing academic papers using Sublime Text 3 &#43; Pandoc</title>
      <link>http://example.org/posts/2019-10-11-sublime-pandoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/posts/2019-10-11-sublime-pandoc/</guid>
      <description>This post explains how to write academic papers using Sublime Text 3 in markdown format and transform the .md file into .docx and pdf files using pandoc.
Prerequisites To write academic papers in markdown format requires a markdown editor, a format trnasformer, maybe also a literature manager. I use Sublime Text 3 as the markdown edit, Pandoc as the format transformer, and Zotero as the literature manager. This section lists the things we need.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>