<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chunyu Ge</title>
    <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Chunyu Ge</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ge-chunyu&#34;&gt;Chunyu Ge&lt;/a&gt; 2019-2026</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ge-chunyu.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>釋《詩經·巷伯》緝緝、捷捷</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2026-01-jiji/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2026-01-jiji/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;《詩經·小雅·節南山之什·巷伯》：“緝緝翩翩，謀欲譖人……捷捷幡幡，謀欲譖言”，毛傳：“緝緝，口舌聲。翩翩，往來貌。……捷捷猶緝緝也。幡幡猶翩翩也。”這是認爲緝緝、捷捷是表示說話聲音的意思。緝緝、捷捷其實是模擬嘴脣頻繁運動，來表示頻繁說話（或者叫多言且煩）的擬聲詞。緝清母緝部、捷從母葉部，兩個字雖然聲母清濁有別，韻母元音不同，但韻尾都是脣音 p。說話的時候嘴脣肯定會動，所以語言中往往會用脣音來表示多言的意思（一般還表示所說的話沒有意義），例如英語中的 blabla、blabber、babble，拉丁語中的 blaterare（來自於 balbus，這個詞可以追溯到原始印歐語中的 *bl-bl-，見 De Vaan, Michiel (2008). &lt;em&gt;Etymological Dictionary of Latin and the other Italic Languages&lt;/em&gt;. 68 頁）。緝緝、捷捷是以這兩個讀音當中的脣音韻尾來形容嘴脣運動，從而表達頻繁地說話的意思。翩翩、幡幡則是形容說話時嘴脣上下翻飛的樣子。《詩經·小雅·鹿鳴之什·四牡》：“翩翩者鵻”（又見《小雅·南有嘉魚之什·南有嘉魚》），是用翩翩形容鳥頻繁扇動翅膀的樣子。說話時嘴脣上下翻飛，和鳥兒飛翔時翅膀頻繁扇動在形態上是相似的。因此，《巷伯》裏的翩翩也應該是形容嘴脣頻繁運動的樣子，而不是毛傳所說的“往來貌” 。幡幡和翩翩聲音相近，也是同樣的意思。《詩經·小雅·魚藻之什·瓠葉》：“幡幡瓠葉”，就是用幡幡來形容葉子上下翻飛的樣子。《巷伯》用緝緝、捷捷和翩翩、幡幡，都是形容那個說壞話的人（“彼譖人”）嘴脣不停運動說壞話的樣子。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>《漢書·律曆志》筆記（6）：世經</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-12-lvlizhi6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-12-lvlizhi6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;這一部分用上面總結的三統曆算法驗算世經。這裏有幾點要提前說明：&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;世經所記載的距上元年數不一致。在計算時有時需要算外減一，有時不需要。這裏用的辦法是：如果所求年份在伐紂克殷 142109 之後、漢高祖元年 143025 以前，距上元年數就要算外減一，其餘年份則不用。具體理由見下面“世經所記距上元年數”部分。&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;世經所記與所引證的經傳有的與三統曆相合，有的不合，但是不合的是極少數，例如所引《武成》“粵若來三月”與世經所列日名不合，見“武王伐紂日名”一段。又如所引《畢命》康王十二年“六月庚午朏”，三統曆推算出是八月庚午朏（見“其他日名”一段）。&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;世經所記時段&#34;&gt;世經所記時段&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;世經是劉歆以三統曆排定的東漢以前年表。從五帝到夏朝，都沒有年數。世經中可考的最早年數從商湯伐桀開始，伐桀之年距上元 141480 歲，歲在大火房五度。伐桀到伐紂克殷之年之間，只有成湯崩年（即太甲元年）有歲數。從伐桀到武王伐紂克殷距上元 142109 年，總共 629 年。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>《漢書·律曆志》筆記（5）：紀術</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-12-lvlizhi5/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-12-lvlizhi5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ge-chunyu.github.io/img/2025-12-lvlizhi/planet.svg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;行星與地球都是圍繞太陽運動的，而這種運動在地球上看來則是相當複雜的。上面這張圖是行星、地球、太陽之間相互位置的示意圖。中間橘色的點代表太陽，下面藍色的點代表地球；實線表示地球軌道，點線代表內行星（水星、金星）的軌道，虛線代表外行星（火星、木星、土星）的軌道。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>《漢書·律曆志》筆記（4）：統術（附歲術）</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-12-lvlizhi4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-12-lvlizhi4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;統術是三統曆的基本曆法計算方法，可以用來計算一年在三統中的位置，該年天正月朔日的干支名稱（也就是日名）、冬至日和其他所有節氣的日名，以及本年是否需要置閏和在哪一個月置閏。除此之外，統術還包括計算天正月朔日日月所在星度、月食時刻等方法。三統曆以建子月，也就是夏正十一月爲曆法的起始，也是每年的第一個月，稱之爲天正。《律曆志》說：&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>《漢書·律曆志》筆記（3）：三統曆算法的基本思路</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-12-lvlizhi3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-12-lvlizhi3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;三統曆曆法計算分爲三個部分，第一部分是年月日、節氣、月食等的計算，叫做統術；第二部分是五大行星出現的時間等的計算，叫做紀術；第三部分是推求特定年份木星所在十二次的哪一次，叫做歲術。下面先解釋三統曆算法的基本思路，之後再依次介紹統術、紀術、歲術的計算方法。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>《漢書·律曆志》筆記（2）:表格與常數</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-12-lvlizhi2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-12-lvlizhi2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;《漢書·律曆志》卷下的主要內容是三統曆的常數、計算法和以三統曆推算的自太皞以來到漢代的年曆。三統曆設置的常數是曆法計算的基礎。三統曆設置的常數，包括用於計算年月日的統母、計算五星運行的紀母，和最重要的太極上元。以下從太極上元開始，依次對這些常數的數值計算和意義進行解釋。三統曆對統法的解釋牽扯到很多律曆和數術的概念，導致原本十分清楚的計算過程難以理解。所以在解釋統母之前，直接將這些數字與三統曆基本基本時間單位的時間長度聯繫起來進行解釋。在統母、紀母部分之後，三統曆還有一份五星運行軌跡、日期、度數的表格，叫做五步。這裏將五步的表格放在常數後面介紹。另外，除了這些常數和五星運行數據之外，三統曆的計算還要用到六十干支表、二十四節氣表、十二次度數表，以及二十八宿距度表，這些表格解釋完常數和五步之後進行介紹。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>《漢書·律曆志》筆記（1）:中國傳統曆法的特點與《漢書·律曆志》的主要內容</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-12-lvlizhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-12-lvlizhi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;中國傳統曆法的特點&#34;&gt;中國傳統曆法的特點&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;中國傳統曆法有以下這些主要特點：&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;用干支記錄日期&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;以朔望月來確定月份&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;以朔望月與回歸年的配合來確定一年的長度，也就是在哪些年份設置閏月，閏月設置在哪個月份&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;除了年月日之外，還有完全由回歸年決定的二十四節氣&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;除了編算年月日、節氣之外，還要推算五大行星的運行&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;以下就對這些特點進行詳細說明。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variables and string in the shell</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-11-shell-string/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-11-shell-string/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have not really grasped the tricky variable use and string operations in the shell, and this post is a cheatsheet of the common variable and string operations in the shell.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;variables&#34;&gt;Variables&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Assigning values to variables, note that &lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt; immediately follows the variable name and it allows no space.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;variable=&#39;value&#39;&#xA;variable=&amp;quot;value&amp;quot;&#xA;variable=value&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are several ways of calling a variable, by &lt;code&gt;$variable&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;${variable}&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;$variable&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;. The curly braces are useful when you need to clearly mark the boundary of the variable name. For example, &lt;code&gt;$variableisvalue&lt;/code&gt; will not output the value of &lt;code&gt;$variable&lt;/code&gt; since the shell interprets the name of the variable as &lt;code&gt;variableisvalue&lt;/code&gt;. To tell the shell where the variable name ends, surround the variable name with curly braces &lt;code&gt;${variable}isvalue&lt;/code&gt;, which is not ambiguous to the shell.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>說丁年</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-10-dingnian/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-10-dingnian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;《文選》李陵《答蘇武書》：“丁年奉使。”李善注：“丁年，謂丁壯之年也。漢書曰：武留匈奴凡十九歲。始以強壯出，及還，鬢髮並白。”黃生《字詁義府合按》卷下“丁壯”：“漢書·高帝紀：‘丁壯若軍旅’，古丁、當同音，丁壯言其年正當壯時也。後語省，遂單呼爲丁，故民年二十成丁。李陵《答蘇武書》：‘丁年奉使’，正謂年在二十左右也。”李善讀丁年爲丁壯之年，而黃生說古代丁、當同音，並且指實丁年是二十成丁之年，也就是說蘇武奉使是在二十歲。說丁、當同音不確，下面再詳細討論；而說蘇武二十歲奉使，則是錯的。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My neovim setup (with Ghostty)</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-11-neovim-setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2025-11-neovim-setup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, I switched from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sublimetext.com/&#34;&gt;Sublime Text&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://neovim.io/&#34;&gt;Neovim&lt;/a&gt; and Neovim has proved to be very efficient. This post showcases my Neovim setup and some useful tips.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I agree with &lt;a href=&#34;https://gdgarcia.ca/posts/2025-09-18-workflow/&#34;&gt;Guilherme D. Garcia&lt;/a&gt; that multiple tools for multiple purposes (RStudio for R, Sublime Text for markdown and $LaTeX$, etc.) is far from perfect, and Neovim indeed provided an integrated way of dealing with all these purposes (markdown/$LaTeX$, R, Python, and many more). It also provides the incredible capabilities of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vim.org/&#34;&gt;Vim&lt;/a&gt; arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>爲什麼是“喝西北風”</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2024-12-xibeifeng/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2024-12-xibeifeng/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;漢語裏人們常常說沒飯吃是“喝西北風”，例如詞典中常舉的吳敬梓《儒林外傳》第四十一回的：“都像你這一毛不拔，我們喝西北風。”那爲什麼是喝西北風，不是喝東南風、西南風呢？網上常見的說法是這跟我國的氣候地形有關。我國冬季吹西伯利亞南下的西北風，而這時正值冬天，如果沒有儲備，就只能忍飢挨餓，所以叫喝西北風。這種說法沒有依據，更何況漢語裏很少說冬天沒有糧食吃。說到沒有糧食，一般都是青黃不接，是指的春季莊稼剛剛播種，尚未長成，而舊穀已經吃完了。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Substitution in Vim with expressions</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2024-09-substitution-vim/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2024-09-substitution-vim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Substitution in vim is very efficient, especially with the help of expressions. This is especially useful for calculations. I discovered this usage when I wanted to insert a list of numbers to the beginning of each line. But before go to the example, let’s take a look at expressions in vim substitution.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The expressions in vim are marked with “=”. This tells vim to treat the contents after “=” as expressions rather than literal texts. For example, vim will treat &lt;code&gt;\=1+1&lt;/code&gt; as 2 rather than the text &lt;code&gt;1+1&lt;/code&gt;. Using &lt;code&gt;\=&lt;/code&gt;, I can insert numbers in the beginning of each line with expressions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convert markdown files to pdf files using pandoc in vim</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2024-08-pandoc-vim/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2024-08-pandoc-vim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am learning vim and I want to migrate my workflow in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sublimetext.com/&#34;&gt;Sublime Text&lt;/a&gt; to vim. One of the things I do most with Sublime Text is to write &lt;a href=&#34;https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-customizing-pdf/&#34;&gt;markdown files&lt;/a&gt; and convert them to pdf files using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pandoc.org/&#34;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;. After some search, I did not find a satisfied plugin which does such a job. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vim-pandoc/vim-pandoc&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;vim-pandoc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; seems to be too powerful. I did some more search and found this &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimandgit.com/posts/vim/advanced/neovim-and-vim-pandoc-batch-convert-markdown-to-html.html&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, which is very informative and I follow the instructions to create my own plugin to convert markdown files to pdf files using pandoc in vim.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A tutorial on generalized additive mixed-effects model (GAMM)</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2024-04-gamm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2024-04-gamm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;preliminaries-the-challenge-of-dynamic-data&#34;&gt;Preliminaries: The challenge of dynamic data&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Phonetics used to concern mostly with static data, such as VOT, formant values at vowel midpoint, or F0 at vowel onset. But as computers are getting more and more powerful, it is common (almost a necessity) to analyze dynamic data. For example, instead of F0 at vowel onset, pitch contour during the voiced parts needs to be analyzed, and similarly, formant trajectories are analyzed instead of formant values at vowel midpoints.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How I backup my data</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2024-03-backup/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2024-03-backup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Digital data is easy to copy and also easy to lose, due to (usually sudden) failure of electronic devices. A good habit is to backup regularly and in different locations. This post is about my solution to data backup.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;classification-of-digital-data&#34;&gt;Classification of digital data&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Digital data can be classified according to their importance and sizes, and the following lists some of the categories based on their importance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Data that can be downloaded online&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Papers and e-books collected from various sources&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Personal photos and videos&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Experimental data and code&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Personal documents and writings&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Data that can be downloaded online is the lease important, since they can be easily accessed online and even it&amp;rsquo;s lost, it can be easily found online. Papers and e-books (or other resources) that are collected from various sources and clearly organized are more important. Some resources are hard to find, and once it is found, it&amp;rsquo;s better to keep it safe and have multiple copies. Personal photos and videos are even more important, to keep a record of ones&amp;rsquo;s life and happy memories.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>說“肘後”</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2023-11-zhouhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2023-11-zhouhou/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;東晉葛洪有《肘後備急方》，取其卷帙短小，可以繫於肘後，隨時查閱的意思。兩漢魏晉時候的人往往會將隨身攜帶的飾物、印章等繫於肘後。文獻中雖然例子不多，但仔細鉤稽，仍可以推測其彷彿。《世說新語·尤悔第三十三》第六條：&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo forced alignment using a Praat script</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2023-09-pseudo-forced-alignment/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2023-09-pseudo-forced-alignment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is very common for phoneticians to ask speakers to read aloud word lists, especially in the field. However, to find a word in a long sound file is very painful and a better solution is to split the long sound file into short files with meaningful file names. I wrote a Praat script for that purpose and to save some time, I also use the script to fill in the transcriptions to the TextGrid file. This post is a documentation of the script, which can be found in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ge-chunyu/praat_scripts/blob/master/splitLongSound.praat&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How I make a linguistic handout</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2023-05-handout/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2023-05-handout/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Making a linguistic handout needs some tricks. Using MS word is not ideal because the output is not that beautiful and linguistic contents are not . In this post I explain how I make a linguistic handout with markdown and of course LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-workflow&#34;&gt;The workflow&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I usually write documents using markdown and convert it to pdf using &lt;a href=&#34;https://pandoc.org/&#34;&gt;pandoc&lt;/a&gt;, as explained in &lt;a href=&#34;https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-customizing-pdf/&#34;&gt;my previous posts&lt;/a&gt;. I have a same head/template for all handouts, so that the style remains the same for a course. I use different LaTeX packages to format various linguistic contents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Export and import pdf bookmarks</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2023-04-pdf-bookmark/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2023-04-pdf-bookmark/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is sometimes useful to export and import the bookmarks of an existing pdf file to a new pdf file with smaller size. This can be easily done using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pdflabs.com/tools/pdftk-the-pdf-toolkit/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pdftk&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;code&gt;pdftk&lt;/code&gt; is available as GUI and commandline tools. In MacOS, it is better to use it in the terminal. After installation of &lt;code&gt;pdftk&lt;/code&gt;, the bookmarks of one pdf file can be extracted from an existing pdf file and imported to a new pdf file using the following lines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to setup an IPA input method</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2022-12-ipa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2022-12-ipa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;use-rime&#34;&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;RIME&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rime.im/&#34;&gt;RIME&lt;/a&gt; is an input method engine. It can run different input method schemas, and of course, IPA. There are two schemas which are available in RIME, &lt;code&gt;yunlong&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;xsampa&lt;/code&gt;. To use these schemas, you need to install RIME. It can be installed on Windows, MacOS and Linux. After installation, there are two files you need to modify to complete the configuration. The first is &lt;code&gt;default.custom.yaml&lt;/code&gt;. My configurations of this file are as below.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>在 LaTeX 中显示生僻字</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2022-11-01-shengpizi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2022-11-01-shengpizi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;在 LaTeX 里显示生僻字是一个棘手的问题。用&lt;code&gt;xeCJK&lt;/code&gt;包可以解决这个问题，而且不用在文件中遇见生僻字就改字体。&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://mirrors.ibiblio.org/CTAN/macros/xetex/latex/xecjk/xeCJK.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xeCJK&lt;/code&gt;包的使用手册&lt;/a&gt;中有&lt;code&gt;FallBack&lt;/code&gt;的选项（8 页），可以用以下两种办法指定生僻字的字体&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-latex&#34;&gt;\setCJKmainfont[FallBack=SimSun-ExtB]{SimSun}&#xA;\setCJKmainfont{SimSun}&#xA;\setCJKfallbackfamilyfont{\CJKrmdefault}{SimSun-ExtB}&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;第一种办法是在指定字体时用&lt;code&gt;FallBack&lt;/code&gt;参数指定备用字体，第二种办法是在指定字体之后再用&lt;code&gt;\setCJKfallbackfamilyfont&lt;/code&gt;指定备用字体。二者是等价的。但是要注意的是，在用&lt;code&gt;FallBack&lt;/code&gt;时，必须在导入&lt;code&gt;xeCJK&lt;/code&gt;宏包时设置&lt;code&gt;AutoFallBack=true&lt;/code&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>说“酿菜”的“酿”</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2022-08-niangcai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2022-08-niangcai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;已刊于《语言文字周报》。&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;酿菜是很多人都很爱吃的菜，比如酿豆腐、酿苦瓜、煎酿三宝等等。所谓酿菜，根据《现代汉语词典》：“烹调方法，将肉、鱼、虾等剁碎做成的馅儿填或塞入掏空的柿子椒、冬瓜等里面，然后蒸或用油煎。”(第六版，949 页)酿菜在各地都广受喜爱，那么“酿”这个词到底是怎么来的呢？&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>春秋时期的天文：十二次与分野</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-08-cq-fenye/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-08-cq-fenye/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;天空中除了位置比较稳定的恒星之外，还有位置时常发生变动的行星。与恒星不同，行星自身并不发光，而是和月亮一样，靠反射太阳光来发光。因此，行星与太阳、地球之间的相对位置不同会导致地球上所能看到行星反射太阳光面积大小不同的情况。同样的原因造成了月圆月缺，行星也有类似的现象，比如金星就有相位变化。但是由于金星离地球较远，又有致密的大气层，所以直到伽利略才通过望远镜发现金星也有相位变化。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>春秋时期的天文：星象</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-08-cq-astrology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-08-cq-astrology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;太阳下山，夜空中就会布满繁星。在浩瀚宇宙中传递了亿万年的星光，由于位置相近或偶然的投影，在夜空中形成了各种形状。人类看到这些形状就会联想到生活中的事物，或是想出新奇的故事。现代 88 个星座的命名有的历史悠久，有的则比较年轻。南天星座大多是大航海时代命名的，因此大多取象于航海仪器，比如六分仪座（Sextans）、望远镜座（Telescopim）。北半球的星座的命名则由来已久，往往是以神话命名的，比如武仙座（Hercules，宙斯的儿子大力士海格立斯）、仙后座（Cassiopeia，古代埃塞俄比亚的王后）。在中国，也有星座是用神话来命名的。《左传·昭公元年》子产给叔向讲了这么一个故事：&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>春秋时期的天文：日食</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-08-cq-eclipse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-08-cq-eclipse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;日升月落，星移斗转，是最鲜明的天体运动。先民在长期观察中，发现气候寒温、草木荣枯与天象之间存在紧密的关系。上古时期，历法还不够成熟，而且也不够普及；又没有准确的计时系统。天象在先民的日常生活中起着极其重要的作用。这就是为什么“三代以上，人人皆知天文”的缘故。到了后世，历法发达，计时系统逐渐准确，而大部分人又不必从事与气候紧密相关的农业劳动，因此，“有问之文人学士而懵然不知者”。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to define aesthetic mappings of ggplot2 within another function</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-03-ggplot-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-03-ggplot-function/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; is great for visualization, but sometimes we need to include &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; functions within another function. &lt;code&gt;ggplot()&lt;/code&gt; uses &lt;code&gt;aes()&lt;/code&gt; to define aesthetic mappings of different variables. The question is: how to define aesthetic mappings when writing functions using &lt;code&gt;ggplot()&lt;/code&gt;? In this post I will present several approaches.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First of all, let&amp;rsquo;s load the required packages and some test data.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;library(ggplot2)&#xA;library(dplyr)&#xA;data(&amp;quot;mtcars&amp;quot;)&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-aes_string&#34;&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;aes_string()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are two standard ways to define aesthetic mappings in &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;aes_string()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;aes_()&lt;/code&gt;. Writing a function using &lt;code&gt;aes_string()&lt;/code&gt; is the same as using &lt;code&gt;aes()&lt;/code&gt;, but calling the function requires passing the variable names as strings to the function.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Writing Praat scripts in a modular way</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-12-praat/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-12-praat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://praat.org&#34;&gt;Praat&lt;/a&gt; is widely used in phonetic research. Working with Praat involves inevitably the &lt;em&gt;Praat scripting&lt;/em&gt;. There are plenty of resources of Praat scripts as well as great tutorials to Praat scripting (see below). Why bother writing Praat scripts oneself?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Praat scripts written by others can be helpful, but even an script is available which offer the functionality one needs, it is seldom exactly what one wants. It is normal to do some tailoring to the scripts. Users of Praat may be great phoneticians, but rarely are they professional programmers. When I write my own Praat scripts, I try to explicitly adopt some principles and conventions to facilitate the reusability of code. This post is about these principles and conventions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>用pandoc生成大型中文文档的痛点与解决方案</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-11-pandoc-large-document/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-11-pandoc-large-document/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pandoc.org&#34;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;是转换文本格式的利器。在用 Pandoc 转换中文文档和生成大型文档时，例如用中文写作毕业论文等时，会遇到一些很麻烦的问题。我在前面的博客里说过我在用 Markdown 写博士毕业论文，这篇博客就我自己的经验讲一下在用 Pandoc 生成大型中文文档的痛点与解决方案。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Customizing pdf output of Pandoc</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-customizing-pdf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-customizing-pdf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am writing my PhD thesis and instead of using &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt;, I want to write it in &lt;code&gt;markdown&lt;/code&gt; together with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pandoc.org&#34;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;. This has several merits. I can easily transform the &lt;code&gt;markdown&lt;/code&gt; file to &lt;code&gt;docx&lt;/code&gt; for my supervisor to revise. It can also easily be transformed to &lt;code&gt;pdf&lt;/code&gt; files through &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt;. However, the default &lt;code&gt;pdf&lt;/code&gt; output doesn&amp;rsquo;t conform to the format my school requires. What I am going to do is to customize the &lt;code&gt;pdf&lt;/code&gt; format to meet the standard of my school.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scraping all the texts of Luxun(鲁迅) from the Internet using Python (用Python爬取《鲁迅全集》)</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-12-scraping-luxun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-12-scraping-luxun/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to do some text mining practices on the texts of &lt;em&gt;Luxun(鲁迅)&lt;/em&gt;, a great Chinese writer. The first step is to get all the texts by &lt;em&gt;Luxun&lt;/em&gt;, and I have no time typing all the texts word by word. So I decided to srape the texts from an online source.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;source-of-the-texts&#34;&gt;Source of the texts&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The texts of &lt;em&gt;Luxun&lt;/em&gt; are scraped from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ziyexing.com/&#34;&gt;子夜星网&lt;/a&gt;. As it claimed, it contains all the texts in the &lt;em&gt;Complete works of Luxun(鲁迅全集)&lt;/em&gt;. I checked it, and so it did.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Writing academic papers using Sublime Text 3 &#43; Pandoc</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-11-sublime-pandoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-11-sublime-pandoc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post explains how to write academic papers using &lt;em&gt;Sublime Text 3&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;markdown&lt;/em&gt; format and transform the .md file into .docx and pdf files using &lt;em&gt;pandoc&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;prerequisites&#34;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To write academic papers in &lt;em&gt;markdown&lt;/em&gt; format requires a &lt;strong&gt;markdown editor&lt;/strong&gt;, a &lt;strong&gt;format trnasformer&lt;/strong&gt;, maybe also a &lt;strong&gt;literature manager&lt;/strong&gt;. I use &lt;em&gt;Sublime Text 3&lt;/em&gt; as the markdown edit, &lt;em&gt;Pandoc&lt;/em&gt; as the format transformer, and &lt;em&gt;Zotero&lt;/em&gt; as the literature manager. This section lists the things we need.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;sublime-text-3-and-plugins&#34;&gt;Sublime Text 3 and plugins&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sublimetext.com/3&#34;&gt;Sublime Text 3&lt;/a&gt; is a text editor that can be used for code, markup and prose. It is lightweight and is suitable for long texts. The followings are several plugins (or packages) we need:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>中国的《伊利亚特》</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2013-08-04-illiad-of-china/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2013-08-04-illiad-of-china/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;希腊的盲诗人荷马写下了《伊利亚特》，以阿喀琉斯的愤怒为线索，讲述了特洛伊战争最后一年的战况；而这场战争是由美女海伦引起的。在同一时期的中国，著名的盲人史学家左丘明也记录了数场由美女夏姬引发的战役，而以申公巫臣的愤怒为线索。在此之前，还有详细的背景交代，充满戏剧色彩，称得上是《左传》中最惊心动魄的故事之一。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Archive</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/archive/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/archive/</guid>
      <description>A complete list of all posts.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/search/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/search/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
