<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>不辍弦歌</title>
    <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on 不辍弦歌</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ge-chunyu.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>用pandoc生成大型中文文档的痛点与解决方案</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-11-pandoc-large-document/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-11-pandoc-large-document/</guid>
      <description>Pandoc是转换文本格式的利器。在用 Pandoc 转换中文文档和生成大型文档时，例如用中文写作毕业论文等时，会遇到一些很麻烦的问题。我在前面的博客里说过我在用 Markdown 写博士毕业论文，这篇博客就我自己的经验讲一下在用 Pandoc 生成大型中文文档的痛点与解决方案。
Pandoc 将 Markdown 生成 pdf 的逻辑 用 Pandoc 将 Markdown 文件生成 pdf，其实是先把 Markdown 格式转换成 LaTeX 格式，再通过 LaTeX 把转换后的 LaTeX 文件生成最终的 pdf 文件。在用 LaTeX 生成 pdf 时，可以指定不同的--pdf-engine，可选的选项有pdflatex、xelatex、lualatex等。
因为 Pandoc 是通过 LaTeX 来生成 pdf 文件的，所以可以通过修改或添加 LaTeX 源文件来修改最终的 pdf 格式。如果不怕麻烦，可以先用 Pandoc 把 Markdown 文件转换成 LaTeX，再在上面自己改格式。
pandoc --standalone test.md -o test.tex  但是，一般的做法是通过给 Pandoc 传递 LaTeX 命令和 Pandoc 自带的参数来修改 pdf 格式的。当然，也可以直接在 Pandoc 的 pdf template 上进行修改。不过 Pandoc 自带的 template 很复杂，一般用--header-includes给自带的 template 加上需要的 LaTeX 命令就可以了。</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Customizing pdf output of Pandoc</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-customizing-pdf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-customizing-pdf/</guid>
      <description>I am writing my PhD thesis and instead of using LaTeX, I want to write it in markdown together with Pandoc. This has several merits. I can easily transform the markdown file to docx for my supervisor to revise. It can also easily be transformed to pdf files through LaTeX. However, the default pdf output doesn&amp;rsquo;t conform to the format my school requires. What I am going to do is to customize the pdf format to meet the standard of my school.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scraping all the texts of Luxun(鲁迅) from the Internet using Python (用Python爬取《鲁迅全集》)</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-12-scraping-luxun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-12-scraping-luxun/</guid>
      <description>I want to do some text mining practices on the texts of Luxun(鲁迅), a great Chinese writer. The first step is to get all the texts by Luxun, and I have no time typing all the texts word by word. So I decided to srape the texts from an online source.
Source of the texts The texts of Luxun are scraped from 子夜星网. As it claimed, it contains all the texts in the Complete works of Luxun(鲁迅全集).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing academic papers using Sublime Text 3 &#43; Pandoc</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-11-sublime-pandoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-11-sublime-pandoc/</guid>
      <description>This post explains how to write academic papers using Sublime Text 3 in markdown format and transform the .md file into .docx and pdf files using pandoc.
Prerequisites To write academic papers in markdown format requires a markdown editor, a format trnasformer, maybe also a literature manager. I use Sublime Text 3 as the markdown edit, Pandoc as the format transformer, and Zotero as the literature manager. This section lists the things we need.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>