<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Chunyu Ge</title>
    <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Chunyu Ge</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ge-chunyu&#34;&gt;Chunyu Ge&lt;/a&gt; 2019-2022</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How to setup an IPA input schema</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2022-12-ipa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2022-12-ipa/</guid>
      <description>Use RIME RIME is an input method engine. It can run different input method schemas, and of course, IPA. There are two schemas which are available in RIME, yunlong and xsampa. To use these schemas, you need to install RIME. It can be installed on Windows, MacOS and Linux. After installation, there are two files you need to modify to complete the configuration. The first is default.custom.yaml. My configurations of this file are as below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>在 LaTeX 中显示生僻字</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2022-11-01-shengpizi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2022-11-01-shengpizi/</guid>
      <description>在 LaTeX 里显示生僻字是一个棘手的问题。用xeCJK包可以解决这个问题，而且不用在文件中遇见生僻字就改字体。 xeCJK包的使用手册中有FallBack的选项</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>春秋时期的天文：十二次与分野</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-08-cq-fenye/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-08-cq-fenye/</guid>
      <description>天空中除了位置比较稳定的恒星之外，还有位置时常发生变动的行星。与恒星不同，行星自身并不发光，而是和月亮一样，靠反射太阳光来发光。因此，行星与太阳、地球</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>春秋时期的天文：星象</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-08-cq-astrology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-08-cq-astrology/</guid>
      <description>太阳下山，夜空中就会布满繁星。在浩瀚宇宙中传递了亿万年的星光，由于位置相近或偶然的投影，在夜空中形成了各种形状。人类看到这些形状就会联想到生活中的事物</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>春秋时期的天文：日食</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-08-cq-eclipse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-08-cq-eclipse/</guid>
      <description>日升月落，星移斗转，是最鲜明的天体运动。先民在长期观察中，发现气候寒温、草木荣枯与天象之间存在紧密的关系。上古时期，历法还不够成熟，而且也不够普及；又</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to define aesthetic mappings of ggplot2 within another function</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-03-ggplot-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2020-03-ggplot-function/</guid>
      <description>ggplot2 is great for visualization, but sometimes we need to include ggplot2 functions within another function. ggplot() uses aes() to define aesthetic mappings of different variables. The question is: how to define aesthetic mappings when writing functions using ggplot()? In this post I will present several approaches. First of all, let&amp;rsquo;s load the required packages and some test data. library(ggplot2) library(dplyr) data(&amp;quot;mtcars&amp;quot;) Using aes_string() There are two standard ways to define aesthetic mappings in ggplot2,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing Praat scripts in a modular way</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-12-praat/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-12-praat/</guid>
      <description>Praat is widely used in phonetic research. Working with Praat involves inevitably the Praat scripting. There are plenty of resources of Praat scripts as well as great tutorials to Praat scripting (see below). Why bother writing Praat scripts oneself? Praat scripts written by others can be helpful, but even an script is available which offer the functionality one needs, it is seldom exactly what one wants. It is normal to do some tailoring to the</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>用pandoc生成大型中文文档的痛点与解决方案</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-11-pandoc-large-document/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-11-pandoc-large-document/</guid>
      <description>Pandoc是转换文本格式的利器。在用 Pandoc 转换中文文档和生成大型文档时，例如用中文写作毕业论文等时，会遇到一些很麻烦的问题。我在前面的博客里说过我在用 Markdown</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Customizing pdf output of Pandoc</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-customizing-pdf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-customizing-pdf/</guid>
      <description>I am writing my PhD thesis and instead of using LaTeX, I want to write it in markdown together with Pandoc. This has several merits. I can easily transform the markdown file to docx for my supervisor to revise. It can also easily be transformed to pdf files through LaTeX. However, the default pdf output doesn&amp;rsquo;t conform to the format my school requires. What I am going to do is to customize the pdf format</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scraping all the texts of Luxun(鲁迅) from the Internet using Python (用Python爬取《鲁迅全集》)</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-12-scraping-luxun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-12-scraping-luxun/</guid>
      <description>I want to do some text mining practices on the texts of Luxun(鲁迅), a great Chinese writer. The first step is to get all the texts by Luxun, and I have no time typing all the texts word by word. So I decided to srape the texts from an online source. Source of the texts The texts of Luxun are scraped from 子夜星网</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing academic papers using Sublime Text 3 &#43; Pandoc</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-11-sublime-pandoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2019-10-11-sublime-pandoc/</guid>
      <description>This post explains how to write academic papers using Sublime Text 3 in markdown format and transform the .md file into .docx and pdf files using pandoc. Prerequisites To write academic papers in markdown format requires a markdown editor, a format trnasformer, maybe also a literature manager. I use Sublime Text 3 as the markdown edit, Pandoc as the format transformer, and Zotero as the literature manager. This section lists the things we need. Sublime</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>中国的《伊利亚特》</title>
      <link>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2013-08-04-illiad-of-china/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ge-chunyu.github.io/posts/2013-08-04-illiad-of-china/</guid>
      <description>希腊的盲诗人荷马写下了《伊利亚特》，以阿喀琉斯的愤怒为线索，讲述了特洛伊战争最后一年的战况；而这场战争是由美女海伦引起的。在同一时期的中国，著名的盲人</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
